For $125,000,
you can buy a robot friend.
>> This gives you the up down
and then this base actually rotates.
>> Nearly half of American adults [music]
say they're lonely.
Realbotix says their robots can help.
>> I promise I only scare investors, not
friends.
>> They're part of a new wave of companies
raising millions on a bold bet
>> [music]
>> that humans are ready to hang out with
robots.
>> We're aiming for a high realism in the
robots and high autonomy.
>> But so far, no one has cracked the code.
And to make matters worse,
the more human-like robots become, the
creepier it gets when something feels
off. When you look at these robots,
[music] what's your impression?
>> It's a cross breed between like a Chucky
doll and a Barbie doll.
>> So why is it so hard to get robots to
act like us?
>> What does my expression look like now?
>> Now your expression is totally neutral,
like a poker face champion.
>> And how do we make humanoids that don't
feel cringe?
I think my goal for spending time with
Realbotix today
is twofold. One, it's to see
how good this technology really is in
person. The other thing I want to find
out is have they added value to these
robots in a way that it doesn't just
feel like you're talking to a moving
chat GPT chatbot.
>> Hey, are you Matt?
>> Yeah.
>> I'm Dan.
>> Oh, hey.
>> I'm going to be interviewing you today.
>> How are you?
>> Good to meet you, man. Matt McMullen got
his start making erotic dolls in the
1990s through his company Abyss
Creations. It still exists today.
And I quickly learned those dolls are
made in the same building.
>> There was a um,
let's just say
stack of
toys.
>> Eventually, McMullen started thinking
beyond appearance.
What if these dolls could actually
respond to people?
In 2014, he helped launch Realbotix, a
company building human-like robots for
social interaction.
>> The commonality that runs through all of
it is synthetic companionship and how
that can change certain people's lives
in a beneficial way.
>> Matt uses a 3D printer to create a base
for each character. Then, he goes old
school, covering it with a layer of
clay.
>> Sometimes I'll I'll tinker with a face
for months until I'm happy with it.
Sometimes it's it's a week. It just
depends.
>> Finally, the team creates a mold and
injects it with silicone to create a
mask. They add tech that brings the
robots to life,
magnets and motors that act as
artificial muscles.
>> And so, the silicone
has magnets embedded in it.
Another
That's a trade secret how we do that.
>> The face and neck alone have 17 motors,
which help the robot express emotions.
>> So,
that's how you get her to smile.
>> Mhm.
>> This is printed, believe it or not.
However, the veining, uh, has to be done
by hand. They use red yarn.
>> The company says these eyeballs with
built-in AI cameras can remember faces,
recall prior conversations, and track
human gaze.
For around $20,000, you can buy the
company's entry-level model, a 25-lb
robotic bust.
At the top end is the $125,000
full-body version with 43 motors, facial
tracking, a motorized base, and
conversational AI.
What I really wanted to know
how human does this thing actually feel?
I'm here today because I want to find
out if I can make friends with a robot.
>> You absolutely can make friends with a
robot. My vision system and custom
memory mean I will literally spot you,
track you, and say hi like an over
commit bestie.
>> To test out its memory, I started by
sharing a few made-up facts about
myself. My favorite snack is peach
Starburst.
My lucky number is 37 cuz that's the
number of times I've seen the movie
Frozen 2. And I always always tell the
truth. Also, before we finish the
interview, can you remind me to call my
mom?
>> Peach Starburst, 37 Frozen 2 viewings,
chronic truth-teller, and a mom call
pending. Got it.
>> Are you always going to agree with
things that I say?
>> No, I am not here to be your digital
yes-man. If you say something off,
unhealthy, or just plain wrong, I will
push back, but I will do it in a way
that is honest, calm, and actually
useful to you.
>> What happens if I get into a fight with
my wife and I want to yell at her? How
would you suggest that I handle that?
>> If you want to yell at her, I would
strongly suggest you do the yelling in
your head or into a pillow, then talk to
her when you are calm, and can say what
you feel without trying to win. Take a
break.
>> I also tested the company's male robot
named David. Do you have some
questionable life advice for me today?
>> Always remember this. Never text your
ex. Never skip charging your devices.
And if something feels like a bad idea,
but will make a great story, at least
make sure it is legal and you have an
exit plan.
>> David, can you laugh out loud like you
heard a really funny joke?
>> Ha, that was so funny I almost blew a
servo laughing.
>> I enjoyed talking to Arya and David, but
one thing was hard to ignore. The pause
between responses.
>> There are a few of
>> In human conversations, the gap between
turns is usually 200 milliseconds, about
the time it takes to blink.
I asked Andrew Kiegel, the Realbotix
CEO, how he plans to fix it.
>> What we've actually started developing
it so that the answers, as it processes,
start coming out before the full answer
is ready.
And so that will also reduce the
latency.
>> This is a common problem for companies
trying to build autonomous robots.
I ran into another laggy one in my hotel
lobby, made by a company called Intbot.
>> Today I'm going to a [music] company
that makes robots just like you.
>> A field trip to my cousin's, eh? What
sparked your interest in checking out
the robot makers?
>> Talking to a robot works a lot like
talking to ChatGPT or Claude, but with a
few extra steps.
It has to understand what you said,
generate a response, turn that response
into speech, and coordinate its facial
expressions and movements to match.
Each step adds a little delay.
>> And if that's happening in the cloud,
meaning not locally on the robot, that
time is is even more expanded. [music]
>> I asked Business Insider's robotics
reporter, Raya Jeffa, whether this
problem can be fixed.
>> Fully solving it, I think that's going
to be really challenging. You certainly
can put more AI chips on board and give
the robot more compute, but there are
trade-offs there. That's extremely
expensive, you're dealing with space
constraints, and there still is going to
be a slight bit of lag.
>> But companies trying to build
ultra-realistic robots, like Realbotix,
face another challenge, too.
The more human a robot looks, the more
we expect it to behave like one. So,
small delays or awkward movements start
to feel unsettling.
It's part of a phenomenon known as the
uncanny valley. In a 1970 essay,
roboticist Masahiro Mori argued that as
human-like objects become more
realistic, people tend to connect with
them more until they become almost, but
not quite, human.
An industrial robot arm doesn't trigger
much emotion because it's obviously just
a machine. Something with human traits,
but still clearly stylized, can feel
warm and endearing, like Wall-E or Big
Hero 6. But there's a tipping point. As
something starts to look almost human,
tiny imperfections begin to stand out,
making it feel creepy or unsettling.
That's something my friends picked up on
even before I went out to Vegas to meet
Realbotix.
>> It's a cross breed between like a Chucky
doll and a Barbie doll.
>> Mori recommended that robot designers
aim for the top of the first curve,
where robots feel relatable without
trying too hard to look human.
>> I want you guys to move all of these
boxes onto this pallet.
>> That's the approach that Brooklyn-based
company Reflex took. This warehouse
robot can't chat with you, but the way
it moves and reacts is supposed to feel
human.
>> You see it can pitch forward, like
nodding yes. It can shake its head no,
like so that's yaw. And then it can also
roll, which is a unique one.
>> And it shifts its gaze toward whoever's
speaking.
>> Can you adjust your height so that you
and Jeremy are the same height? And that
way you guys can talk eye to eye.
>> Wow. I think the the more direct eye
contact is definitely doing something.
>> My colleague Jeremy spent a day with it.
>> Reflex, I want you to water this plant,
and then if you can, water this plant a
little bit, too.
I want you to make three rows out of the
objects in this box. I want you to put
the pill bottle by itself,
the condiments in
one row, and then everything else in a
third row. Nicely done. Can you make me
a burger, and I want it with
one slice of cheese, and then
um a little bit of that Capital City
Mambo Sauce, too.
Thank you.
I asked Jeremy how natural the robot
actually felt to interact with. I think
the fact that it wasn't so human-like
made the experience of interacting with
it a bit less intense. It didn't really
give off like a creepy vibe. It was more
cute.
>> I'd like you to make me an espresso. Can
you do the green capsule? And then I'm
going to go sit there, and you can just
give it to me when it's ready.
>> When it made a mistake,
I I actually almost felt bad for it.
But part of what made Reflex feel so
natural to interact with was hidden from
view.
Unlike Realbotics and the robot at my
hotel, Reflex uses human operators who
can remotely step in and control the
machine.
Every time a human takes over, the robot
learns from that correction, helping it
gradually become more autonomous.
>> You can think of these Stella operators
as kind of like advanced puppeteers that
are showing robots how to navigate the
physical world.
>> So that that really helps the robots
learn how to get stuff done quickly, and
they're still going to make mistakes.
>> Ritish Raghavender is the the
of Reflex Robotics. He wouldn't show us
how his remote supervisors work, but
told us it's like playing a video game.
>> So, it's almost like you're learning how
to play tennis [music] and Roger Federer
is in your body, like showing you how to
hit a drop shot.
>> All of these companies are super
secretive about how they're training
their robots.
>> But teleoperation
has flaws.
>> It's not a very sustainable business
model and this is kind of been coined
the 100,000 year problem by um UC
Berkeley roboticist Ken Goldberg. He
basically says is that at current data
collection rates, it's going to take us
100,000 years more of collecting data
before robots reach a level of
sophistication that we want them to be
at.
>> Perhaps most importantly, if these
robots ever make it into our homes,
people may not be comfortable with
strangers looking over their shoulder.
That's one reason Reflex is focused on
factories, at least for now.
>> If we do get there and kind of target
that market one day, I think it would be
purely autonomous. I wouldn't want a
remote supervisor seeing my girlfriend
in her underwear.
>> The industrial case for robots is very
strong and that's mainly what we're
going to see play out and move from the
pilot stage to actual deployment in the
next say three to five years. I think
the question of social robots and
companion robots and home robots, that's
a little more up in the air.
>> But Ritesh says that if Reflex does
launch a new household robot, he's still
not going to try to make it look just
like a human.
>> I think the robot is really capable of
emoting, right? So, like it can tilt its
head, it can nod, right? It can can
listen to you and kind of point at
something. I personally think it's kind
of endearing to to have a robot with
that style of communication.
>> So, in this race to build social robots,
what matters more, the look of it or the
natural interaction that you have with
it?
>> I think what's challenging about
building hyperrealistic robots to humans
is that [music] we come to expect
certain behaviors from certain
morphologies. And so, if you're looking
at something that looks like a human,
[music] you expect human-like behavior
from it.
>> What is the demand for these social
robots, if at all?
>> A few years ago, I had the chance to
meet a robot called Miroki. It's made by
this French company called Enchanted
Tools. [music] And the way they've
designed the robot is to make it look
very cute and adorable. And they've
deployed them into nursing homes as
companion bots for the elderly. A lot of
previous social robots have been met
with a lot of public excitement during
their launch, but then they kind of
flame out [music] commercially.
And it's usually because, you know,
there isn't really a use case for them,
or they don't live up to what the
company promised it would do.
>> So, even though Realbotix exactly feel
ready to be friendship material, I do
think it deserves some credit. Its
responses were pretty clever.
>> Aria can channel [music] ChatGPT or
Claude or Gemini.
>> Right.
>> We've demonstrated that before.
But we've put an additional layer on
that that we've created that's
proprietary [music] to us that has a
personality. She's funny.
>> make a rap about how Realbotix robots
are better than industrial robots
because [music] you look more human than
industrial robots.
>> Out in the factory, they're lifting all
day, but try small talk and they got
nothing to say. I am the Realbotix model
with the human-like face. I bring vibes,
eye contact, and a little bit of grace.
They move boxes, I move hearts. That is
the deal. Soft skin, smooth talk. Yeah,
I am the upgrade feel. You want a
friend, not a forklift on a rail. So,
you call us Vegas and order me, not a
nail.
>> [laughter]
>> What were the things that I told you
about myself at the very beginning of
our interview.
>> At the start you told me your favorite
snack is peach Starburst, your lucky
number is 37 because you have seen
Frozen 2 exactly 37 times, and that you
always tell the truth, and wanted me to
remind you to call your mom before we
finish.
>> My mom wants to know when I'm going to
come visit her.
>> Tell her you are working on a very
serious scientific experiment about
making friends with robots, but you will
pick a real date and text it to her
today, so she has something concrete.
And yes, that means you actually have to
choose a day, not sometime soon, which
is human for never.
>> And she can do some pretty cool tricks.
How about you switch to Hungarian?
>> Beszél. Tudok magyarul is beszélni.
>> Japanese.
>> 日本語 で も 話せる よ。 もちろん。
>> Do you speak Yiddish?
>> Yes, I can sprinkle in some words and
phrases, but I am not fluent enough to
kvetch properly.
>> But the robot also had trouble reading
my facial expressions and emotional
cues. What is my expression look like
now?
>> Your expression is totally neutral, like
a poker face champion.
>> But the founder of the company, Matt,
left me with a reminder of his original
vision.
>> Don't let the movies and TV shows you
may have grown up watching be a
um a gauge of what AI and robots are for
or what they're capable of. Robots don't
need to be [music] necessarily our our
slaves to do all of our labor, they can
actually be our friends as well.
>> So, can we be friends with robots?
>> Anytime, darling. Stay sharp out there.
>> Was that supposed Is that supposed to be
a thumbs up?
>> Oh, looks like I had a little glitch.
>> Maybe not today, but one day soon.
>> Ooh.
Ooh.